Miscellaneous letters collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Richardson M[aurice] H., Boston, to O.T. Osborne, 1899 March 20 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  He tells Oborne when he will arrive in New Haven by train and what equipment he needs to give his lecture.
- Roberts, W., The Times, London, to Edward C. Streeter, London, 1925 March 31 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  With Roberts' article, "Notes on Sales. Two Ronsard Exhibitions," from the Times Literary Supplement, 1925 March 12, and a page of handwritten directions for Streeter to visit Roberts.
- Roget, Peter Mark, to Dr. [William Pulteney] Alison, 1821 April 24 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Roget encloses a testimonial (not present) possibly to further Alison's appointment to the medical faculty of the University of Edinburgh. Letter purchased from Myers & Co., 1953.
- Roget, Peter Mark, to L. A. De la Chaumette, Esq., 1833 January 18 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Purchased from Myers & Co., 1953.
- Rolleston, Humphry Davy, Haslemere, 2 letters to Arnold C. Klebs, 1934 September 29 - 1936 November 14 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Removed from Arnold Klebs' copy of Rolleston's The Right Honourable Sir Thomas Clifford Allbutt ... A Memoir (1929).
- Rolleston, Humphry Davy, to Dr. C. H. Bunting, Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore, 1905 November 11 - 1905 December 8 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  From Dr. Bunting, June 1954.
- Routh, Martin Joseph, Magdalene College, Oxford, 2 letters to Rev. Dr. B...ney [?], 1833 February 13 - 1852 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  With these letters are a list of Routh's dates and appointments and a letter from Lord Derby to Dr. B [?] asking him to forward his autograph inscription to the "venerable President of Magdalen College" [i.e. Dr. Routh].
- Sahli, Hermann, Bern, 9 letters to Arnold C. Klebs, 1912-1931 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Folder also includes a draft reply of Klebs to Sahli, 1912 July 22.
- Sahli, Hermann, Bern, 2 letters to Esther Rosencrantz, 1914 June 14 (postmark) - 1930 January 1 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Postcard, 1914 announcing the sudden death of Hugo Kronecker and an obituary written by Sahli for Der Bund, 1914 June 8. Items donated by Esther Rosencrantz to John Fulton in 1949 and 1950.
- Sarton, George, The Belgian Scholarship Committee, Washington, D.C., to Edward C. Streeter, Boston, 1916 May 3 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Sarton mentions his hope that Harvard will appoint him a lecturer for two years.
- Sassoon, Ruby [London], to Edward C. Streeter, 1928 March 30 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  About her father's price for the Persian astrolabe that Streeter saw.
- Sawyer, Asa, Dillsburgh [Pa.], to Levi Bartlett, Kingston, N. H., 1818 April 16 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  On a posible herbal preventative of hydrophobia, of a smallpox epidemic and his vaccination of eight children in a family. Purhased from Symmachus Trading Co., Boston, 1950.
- Scales, William, Lynn, to Thomas Jefferson, President of the United States, 1801 May 5 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Letter by a supporter of Jefferson concerns religion. Purchased by John Fulton from Argosy, 1958. Folder includes correspondence with the American Philosophical Society, 1958, in an attempt to identify William Scales.
- Selye, Hans, Montreal, to C. N. H. Long [New Haven], Christmas 1954 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Given to Ferenc Gyorgyey, Historial Librarian, in 1969.
- Seymer, Lucy, [London], 2 letters to Arnold C. Klebs, 1932 October 17 - 1932 October 26 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Concerning her recent book,General History of Nursing, and possible translations of it into French and German. Letters removed from Klebs' copy of Lucy Seymer,General History of Nursing (1931). There is also a 1932 imprint of the book.
- Seymour, George Dudley, New Haven, to Harry B. Ferris [Yale School of Medicine], 1927 February 1 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Comments on Ferris's article "Early Medical Teachers in Connecticut" and laments the passing away of the country doctor. Donated by Mrs. Davenport Hooker via Herbert Thoms.
- Sherrington, Charles S., Liverpool, to Dr. Mond, 1901 November 18 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  On research on "the physiology of the anthropoid brain."
- Shiga, K[iyoshi], Tokyo, postcard to C. H. Bunting, Johns Hopkins, Baltimore, 1904 October 12 (Box 3 M-Sh)
  Gift of Dr. Bunting, January 1953.
- Silliman, Benjamin, New Haven, to Dr. John Torrey, New York, 1821 July 28 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Received from Henry Schuman, January 1947.
- Silliman, Benjamin, New Haven, to Robert Gilmore, Baltimore, 1832 January 28 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Given by Stanhope Bayne-Jones, Yale University School of Medicine, to John Fulton, January 6, 1947.
- [Silliman, Benjamin] Three letters to Silliman by George Jones and W. Turk concerning a remarkable case of resuscitation, 1836 August 1- 1836 October 19 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  W. Turk, formerly surgeon of the frigate President, recounts at length the case of a sailor William Kemble, aboard the frigate, who was just pronounced dead on January 17, 1814, but then addressed his messmates on moral issues. "Resuscitation was never known after putrefaction had commenced." The folder contains George Jones to Silliman, 1836 October 19, with a copy of a report made by W. Turk, and two letters by Turk to Silliman on the resuscitation, 1836 August 1, and 1836 November 30. The letters were puchased from Argosy Book Stores, New York, in April 1949.
- Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., New York, to Mr. Molineux, 1858 November 8 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  From Henry Schuman, January 1947.
- Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., to G. Hastings Grant, 1858 (Box 4 Si-Z)
- Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., New Haven, to John Torrey, 1858 June 25 (Box 4 Si-Z)
- Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., Yale College Laboratory, to J[oseph] M. Wightman, Boston, 1845 September 24 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  The letter includes a list of apparatus needed for the Yale College Laboratory. Benjamin Silliman, Jr., may have been acting on behalf of his father, Benjamin Silliman, professor of chemistry. Letter donated by Morris Tyler, of Gumbart, Corbin, Tyler & Cooper, Counsellors at Law, New Haven, February 1947. Folder includes correspondence of John Fulton and Morris Tyler, February 1947.
- Simpson, James Y., Edinburgh, 3 letters to Dr. Ramsbottom and 2 unidentified recipients, 1848 October 4 and no date (Box 4 Si-Z)
  On obstetrics, anesthesia, and obstetrical instruments. Purchased by John Fulton from the Scribner Book Store, New York, December 1955. Folder includes transcripts and related correspondence of John Fulton with Harold E. Graves, Scribner Book Store, and with Nicholas M. Greene, professor of anesthesiology at Yale, November-December 1955.
- Singer, Charles, [London], to Edward C. Streeter, 1925 June 1 (Box 4 Si-Z)
- Sloane, Hans, Sir, [Royal Society, London], to Savary of Shiffton[?], Esq., "near Exeter", 1730 July 21 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Thanks the recipient for his paper on the magnet and magnetism, and apologized for the delay in reading it at a meeting, because of Dr. Rutty, secretary of the Royal Society, who was ill and had recently died. The paper was finally read and will soon be published.
  Purchased in or somewhat before 1952, from Peter Murray Hill, London. Folder contains correspondence between W. N. Lawfield, New Malden, Surrey, England, and Madeline Stanton, July-August 1952.
- Smith, Alexander, Glasgow, to G. H. Lewes, no date (Box 4 Si-Z)
  On editors and literary publishing.
- Smith, Herbert E., 3 letters to Harry Burr Ferris, 1910-1913 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Smith was Dean of Yale School of Medicine, 1885-1810, and Harry Burr Ferris was professor of anatomy. The letters are dated Woodmont, Conn., 1910 October; Los Gatos, California, 1913 May 19; and Los Gatos, California, [no year] December 17.
- Smith, J. Talcott, Hanover [Dartmouth] Medical College, 11 letters to Captain Chauncy Barnard, Hartford, 1812 August 16 - 1813 April 18 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  These letters are mostly about Smith trying to obtain payment from Barnard for oats. Several of the letters mention Dr. Nathan Smith. "Letters from the collection of Dr. Walter Steiner, secured by Dr. [Herbert] Thoms from the Steiner Sisters."
- Smith, Nathan, Hanover, N.H., to Mason F. Cogswell, Hartford, Conn., 1813 February 11 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Response by Nathan Smith, professor at Darmouth Medical School, to letters from Mason F. Cogswell, a leading Hartford physician and surgeon. Smith had been offered the position of professor of medicine and surgery at the Medical Institution of Yale College which would begin its first session in the fall of 1813. Cogswell had been offered the position previously but had turned it down. Smith discusses anatomical preparations and books for the new school and an epidemic disease in the Hanover area. He plans to meet Cogswell in person. This letter is the gift of Archives and Special Collections, University of Louisville, 2017.
- Smith, Nathaniel, Philadelphia, to Nathan Smith, New Haven, 1795 January 20 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Nathaniel Smith (1762-1822) and Nathan Smith (1770-1835) were brothers born in Woodbury Connecticut. Both became lawyers and politicians in Connecticut. Nathan Smith, a judge, served as U.S. Senator from Connecticut from 1833 to 1835. Nathaniel Smith served as a member of the U.S. House of Representatives from 1795 to 1799. This letter, written presumably when Nathaniel Smith was in Congress in Philadelphia, concerns a legal case of Baron & Curtis. The letter refers to Benedict and Daggett.
- Smith, Nathaniel, Woodbury, to Nathan Smith, New Haven, 1811 August 17 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  See note for previous folder. Nathaniel Smith is concerned about the health of his son Nat who is studying in New Haven. He is worried that the doctor by his treatments has "driven the disorders of his body into his head," and asks his brother in New Haven to report on his health.
- Spallanzani, Lazzaro, Pavia, to Marchese Girolamo Lucchesini, 1780 June 29 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Purchased from Bader, May 1958.
- Sperry, N. D., U.S. House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., to O. T. Osborne, New Haven, 1900 December 12 (Box 4 Si-Z)
- Steele, H. B., M.D., Winsted, Conn., to "Friend doctor", 1867 September 2 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Hand written letter on the letterhead of "Office of the Solar Caustic Patent, for the New Process of Treating, Cancers, Mole, Birth-Marks, Skin Excrescences..." The letter promotes the product which appears to be an instrument.
- Steig, William, New York, to Clements C. Fry, no year April 7 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  William Steig was a cartoonist for the New Yorker. In the letter, Steig is sending an original drawing of a cartoon to Fry. The folder also contains a copy of the published cartoon. See Susan Wheeler,Five Hundred Years of Medicine and Art, cat. 135.10.
- Sternberg, George M., Surgeon General's Office, War Department, to O.T. Osborne, New Haven, 1899 July 27 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Official acknowledgement form for Osborne's gift to the Surgeon General's Library of a copy of "The Progress of Medicine."
- Sternberg, George M., Havana, to William Henry Welch, 1889 June 20 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Sternberg asks Welch to send a culture of "Brieger's bacillus" to compare with a very pathogenic bacillus he found in the intestines of yellow fever cases.
- Sullivan, John L., New Delhi, India, 2 letters to Madeleine Brown, New Haven, [1945] January 9 - [1945] June 27 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  John L. Sullivan was with the U.S. military in India. He is probably the John L. Sullivan who graduated from Yale School of Medicine in 1951.
- Stewart, Charles H., Secretary, University of Edinburgh to "the Secretary, Yale University Medical School", 1954 February 11 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Document with large red seal signed by the Secretary to the University, Charles H. Stewart, introducing Douglas Guthrie, M.D. who goes to Yale "not merely as a visiting Lecturer but as an accredited representative of the University of Edinburgh charged with the delivery of a message of good will and cordial greeting."
- Swieten, Gerard, Frieherr van, Vienna, to "Monsieur", 1761 October 17 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Congratulates the recipient and his wife on the successful birth of a child and praises the wife's decision to breastfeed rather than hire a wet nurse. Discusses the recent death of [Petrus van] Musschenbroek.
- Symington, Clark, Paisley, Scotland, to Stanhope Bayne-Jones, 1936 September 8 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Concerning the presentation to Bayne-Jones of a china bleeding bowl from the collection of Sir Hugh Reid. Bayne-Jones was dean of the Yale School of Medicine.
- Tennant, Charles J., Franklin, Conn., and Norfolk, Va., 3 letters, 1861 and n.d. (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Charles J. Tennant was a native of Windsor, Connecticut, who served as a surgeon with the Northern army in the Civil War. The first letter to "Cousin Albert" (Albert Morrison, Windsor, Conn.), 1861 August 4, discusses haying and comments on the Battle of Bull Run, Abraham Lincoln, and William Seward. The other letters are from Norfolk, Virginia to "Dear Doctor, 1863 June 26; and to "Dear Doctor," [no year] June 15.
- Tiedemann, Friedrich, Heidelberg, to William Sharpey, London, 1838 November [9?] - 1839 April 14 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Only the second letter is clearly addressed to "Professor Sharpey." Letters were removed from Tiedemann and Leopold Gmelin, Recherches expérimentales, physiologiques et chimiques sur la digestion (1826-1827).
- Tingry, Pierre-Francois, Geneva, to Simon-André Tissot, 1790 April 14 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Letter on inoculation for smallpox. Collected and tipped onto a sheet of information by Arnold C. Klebs.
- Trudeau, Edward L., Saranac Lake, N.Y., to O. T. Osborne, New Haven, 1899 February 4 (Box 4 Si-Z)
- Tyndall, John, Alp Lusgen, Brieg, Switzerland, to "Gentlemen" [The Youth's Companion], 1887 October 5 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Tyndall wants to be sure that the articles he writes for this magazine can be republished later in collected form. Letter collected by Harvey Cushing (possibly via Cushing's father Henry Kirke Cushing).
- Tyson, James, Philadelphia, to O. T. Osborne, 1900 May 17 (Box 4 Si-Z)
- Vicq d'Azyr, Félix, Paris, to S.-A. Tissot, 1791 August 18 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Probably the gift of Arnold C. Klebs,
- Vincent, Jean H., Collège de France, Paris, to Milton Senn, Washington University, St. Louis, 1932 April 19 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  He would like to send "a provision of the new anticolibacillary serum," but it is illegal to send therapeutic serums to the United States. He suggests Senn write to Dr. G. W. McCoy, Director of the U.S. Public Health Service for authorization.
  Letter donated by Byron H. Waksman, Chairman of the Department of Microbiology, Yale University School of Medicine, February 1970.
- Wallace, Alfred R., Parkstone, Dorset, to A. M. Bell, 1899 February 14 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Wallace is unable donate more toward the purchase of Mr. Harrison's collection for the Kent County Museum. Letter was removed from Leonard Huxley, Life and Letters of Thomas Henry Huxley, 3 vols. London, 1903.
- Warren, John, Boston, to Leverett Hubbard, New Haven (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Warren congratulates Leverett Hubbrad, president of the New Haven County Medical Society, founded in 1784, on the publication of the first issue of the Society's Transactions in 1788.
- Watkins, Samuel C. G., Letters received, A-H, 1923-1931 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Watkins was a dentist in Montclair, New Jersey, who wrote to notables mainly to get their autographs. In this group of letters to physicians, medical philanthropists, and public health promoters, Watkins asked various general questions to get the recipient to respond. For example, he posited a nephew in high school and asked whether medicine was a good field to enter. Other questions concerned public health based on recent news. Some recipients answered at length. Letter writers have been arranged alphabetically.
  Writers in this folder include Donald B. Armstrong, W. H. Bates, George Emerson Brewer, Alexis Carrel, William E. Chenery, Emile Coué, H. S. Cumming, William Darrach, George Draper, David L. Edsall, Kendall Emerson, Nelli B. Foster, Louis I. Harris, and Floyd G. Haviland.
  These letters seem to have been sent from Sterling Memorial Library to the Historical Library some time before 1968. They are related to the Samuel C. G. Watkins Autograph Collection (MS 698) at Manuscripts and Archives.
- Watkins, Samuel C. G., Letters received J-R, 1923-1931 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Writers in this folder include Walter B. James, John Harvey Kellogg, Samuel J. Kopetsky, George W. Kosmak, Charles J. Mayo, William J. Mayo, John McGrath, George R. Minot, Frank J. Monaghan, R. Ottonlengui, and Willard O. Rappelye.
- Watkins, Samuel C. G., Letters received S-W, 1891, 1921-1931 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Writers in this folder include Florence R. Sabin, Emma Fall Schofield, C. S. Stockton, Nathan Straus, George E. Vincent, Frederic A. Washburn, James W. White, Ira S. Wile, John E. Weeks, C.-E. A. Winslow, Francis Carter Wood, Thomas D. Wood, and an unidentified writer. The folder also contains a copy of vital statistics of various countries, ca. 1922.
- Watkins, Tobias, Washington, D.C., to the Secretary of the Navy, 1823 December 5 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  From H. W. Liebert, February 1960.
- Weber, Frederick Parkes, London, to Havelock Ellis, 1938 October 7 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Thanks Ellis for sending a photograph of James Hinton to compare to a that photo he has. He doesn't think his photo is of the same person. The letter was removed from Havelock Ellis's copy of Frederick Parkes Weber,Some thoughts of a doctor (London, 1935). With the letter are corrected page proofs for a Weber article in Medical Press (August 1, 1917).
- Weigert, Carl, Frankfurt, postcard to Dr. Walter Klotz, New York, 1901 January 1 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Given to John Fulton by Dr. Esther Rosencrantz, November 1950.
- Welch, William Henry, Baltimore Club [Baltimore], to Dr. L. K. Musselman, 1922 November 26 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Luther Kyner Musselman received an M.D. from Johns Hopkins in 1919 and a Ph.D. from Yale in 1923. Welch accepts the invitation of the Yale Chapter of the Gamma Alpha Fraternity to a dinner at the Graduate Club. Folder includes envelope and a copy of the cartoon, "Some Welch Rabbits." Donated by Dr. Musselman, January 1964.
- Welch, William Henry, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, to Arthur H. Ruggles, Butler Hospital, Providence, 1929 October 7 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Two copies of what might be a facsimile letter. Welch agrees "to preside at the twentieth anniversary dinner commemorative of the founding of the mental hygiene movement." Refers to Clifford Beers. Received from Ira Hiscock some time before 1967.
- Welch, William Henry, Baltimore, to O. T. Osborne, 1898 June 6 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  On the letterhead of the Journal of Experimental Medicine of which Welch served as editor. This may relate to Osborne's request to become a member of a society.
- Whipple, George H., Rochester, New York, reference for William J. Messinger for a Yale fellowship, 1939 February 2 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Reference for the Alexander Brown Coxe Memorial Fellowship for Research in the Biological Sciences, Yale University School of Medicine.
- Williams, Clark, Lebanon, Conn., to Capt. James Powers, Waterford, Conn., 1813 May 29 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Williams asks Powers if the traveling physician Moses Hale, who claimed to have "cured" Powers's wife of "the Consumption," is truthful or an "imposter." Hale has not thus far helped Williams's "complaint."
  Letter was purchased by John Fulton from Mrs. Frances Edwards, Suffield, Conn., January 1951. Correspondence on the purchase is included in the folder.
- Williams, Francis H., Boston, to O. T. Osborne, 1900 March 8 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Sends Osborne an abstract (not included) of what he had the pleasure of presenting at the Yale Medical Alumni Association on March 28.
- Wilson, William C., Philadelphia, 2 letters to Eugene Carter, New Haven, 1886 May 12 - 1886 July 14 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  "Prof. William Wilson" has a system of "nerve cure" described in print on the back of his stationery that cures a wide variety of conditions. He sends Carter an "Actina," which includes a battery for use for his eyes. Wilson claims myopia or nearsightedness can be cured with it.
- Winslow, Forbes Benignus, Hammersmith, London, 17 letters to Sir John Philippart, 1847 March 8 - 1859 January (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Two letters undated. Processed by Madeline Stanton, but no information on provenance.
- Witherell, H. M., Troy, New York, to William Duffy, Albany, New York, 1886 December 10 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  H. M. Witherell, M.D., wants give up his professional practice for that of the stage. He asks for a "trial." The letter was the gift of L. Cohen, Argosy Books, 1952.
- Wood, Laura, Washington, D.C., to William Henry Howell, Johns Hopkins, 1941 November 30 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  She is writing a children's book on Walter Reed and asks Howell for details of Walter Reed's stay at Johns Hopkins studying physiology in 1881. The book was published as Laura Wood Roper, Walter Reed: Doctor in Uniform(New York: J. Messner, [1943]).
- [Woodford, William] Petition of John N---, Darlington, to Lord Henry, Earl of Lincoln, concerning William Woodford, 1755 January 23 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Concerns the salary of William Woodford, Professor of Physick at Oxford. Petititon was the gift of Dr. Richard Hunter, London, to John Fulton, 1956.
- Woodruff, Timothy L., Lieutenant Governor, Albany, to O. T. Osborne, New Haven, 1900 January 31 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  On Osborne's effort to prevent his son, John Woodruff, from getting the measles, and what to do if he does get the measles. Letter sent to the Yale Medical Library after Osborne's death.
- Woodward, Joseph Janvier, Surgeon-General's Office, Washington, D.C., 4 letters to Jabez Hogg, 1870 April 23 - 1876 June 28 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  On medical microscopy and micro-photography. Woodward was one of the first physicians to apply micro-photography to pathology. Jabez Hogg was a British ophthalmologist.
  Letters and a cabinet photograph of Woodward were purchased from Myers & Co., May 1954. Photograph has been transferred to the Library's photograph collection.
- Wright, Frank W., New Haven, to N. O. B. Wingrete [?], Secretary of the Wisconsin Board of Health, 1901 October 7 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Wright was the Health Officer of New Haven.
- Young, Thomas, Selkirk [England], to John Bostock, Liverpool, 1795 August 12 (Box 4 Si-Z)
  Letter is partly about religion and his willingness to go to plays and to dance. Letter was purchased by John Fulton from Gurney and given to the Library in October 1955.